Guide to the Matthew Vassar Papers, 1730-1975
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Matthew Vassar Papers
1730-1975
1815-1870
Vassar, Matthew, 1792-1868
18 cubic feet (47 boxes, 1 oversize folio box); 15 oversize map folders; 6 framed items
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Biographies, autographs, correspondence, diaries, maps, photographs created by and relating to Matthew Vassar, founder of Vassar College.
Biographical Note
Matthew Vassar, born in the County of Norfolk, England, emigrated with his parents and other family members to Dutchess County, N.Y., in 1796. The Vassars were a family of brewers, and Matthew set up his own brewery in Poughkeepsie in 1811. His other enterprises included land dwellings in Michigan and an interest in a whaling fleet and dock in Poughkeepsie.
Married to Catherine Valentine in 1813, Vassar made a comfortable fortune. After a trip to Europe in 1845, he thought seriously of using his means to endow a hospital. About that time, however, he met Milo P. Jewett, who had bought a Poughkeepsie girl’s school from Vassar’s niece Lydia Booth. Jewett apparently interested Vassar in the idea of establishing a college for women. Vassar College was chartered in 1861 and opened its doors to students in 1865. It was not the first venture in higher education for women, but the extensive advertising and publicity for the college brought the question of women’s education to popular attention with greater force than ever before. Matthew Vassar strongly believed in women’s mental capacity, in proving that woman’s mind was equal to man’s; and he intended that his college should both prove that point and prepare women to live in the modern world.
Though he was not polished in manner of speech, Matthew Vassar was undeniably a man of remarkable creativity, intelligence, and determination. Vassar’s experiment was responsible for the appearance of many colleges for women in England and in this country, and encouraged coeducation, as well, in state-supported institutions.
Chronology
29 Apr 1792 Matthew Vassar born in East Dereham, Norfolk, England, to James and Ann Vassar.
1796 The Vassar Family moved to the United States with parents and siblings.
1797 The Vassar Family purchased a farm in Dutchess County.
1801 The Vassar Family sold the farm and moved to Poughkeepsie to start a brewery.
1807 Matthew ran away from home to avoid an unpalatable apprenticeship as a tanner.
1810 Matthew returned to Poughkeepsie with $150 he'd saved while working for merchants in Newburgh.
1810 Matthew began working at the family brewery.
10 May 1811 The brewery burned to the ground, uninsured.
11 May 1811 John Guy Vassar, Matthew's brother, died examining the debris.
1811 In his grief, James Vassar abandoned Poughkeepsie and Matthew started a new brewery called M. Vassar and Co.
1812 Matthew opened Poughkeepsie's first oyster bar.
7 Mar 1813 Matthew married Catherine Valentine.
1832 John Guy Vassar and Matthew Vassar, Jr. (Matthew's late brother's sons), became partners in the brewery.
1845 With income swelled by great success in business, Matthew and Catherine traveled to Europe. While there, they visited Guy Hospital in London, named after John Guy, a Vassar relative and the institution's sole benefactor. The visit inspired Matthew to seriously consider the future of his fortunes and the legacy of his accomplishments.
1854 Lydia Booth, Matthew's niece and mistress of Poughkeepsie's Cottage Hill Seminary (for girls), died. It was Booth who fomented the idea of founding a college for women to ensure the Vassar name a prominent place in history. The idea was further encouraged by Milo P. Jewett, Booth's successor at Cottage Hill.
1856 Matthew hired an architect to begin planning a college for women.
Jan 1861 The Legislature of the State of New York passed the bill incorporating Vassar Female College.
26 Feb 1861 Vassar's Board of Trustees held its first meeting and elected Milo P. Jewett the college's first president.
4 Jun 1861 Ground was broken for the College's first building.
1863 Catherine Vassar died.
Apr 1864 Jewett resigned following a series of disagreements with the founder. John Howard Raymond was elected as his successor.
26 Sep 1865 Vassar College opened, welcoming 353 students from 22 states.
30 Apr 1866 Vassar celebrated its first Founder's Day, in honor of Matthew's birthday.
23 Jun 1868 Matthew Vassar died during a meeting of Vassar's Board of Trustees.
Scope and Content Note
Much of the correspondence, especially personal, is missing because after Matthew Vassar’s death, his nephew, Matthew Vassar Jr., sold all of the letters and papers in the house to the rag and old paper dealers to benefit the estate. Much of the remaining correspondence concerns his business. Upon the death of Matthew Vassar’s nephew and business partner, Oliver H. Booth (1823-1896), a large accumulation of “all and any paper that had been written on” covering most of the nineteenth century was found in the brewery, and Henry Booth (1849-1929)[son/nephew of Oliver H. Booth?] kept those which were considered worth keeping. They were donated to Vassar College in 1964 by Deling Booth, Henry Booth's grandson, and are marked in the register with a double asterisk (**). They are described as written by Matthew Vassar to his firm.
Among the letters to the college, there are a number of people with whom Matthew Vassar maintained a substantial correspondence. These include Martin Brewer Anderson at the University of Rochester (where the originals are held); Sarah J. Hale, editor of Godey’s Lady’s Book, a strong early supporter who was responsible for the removal of “Female” from the college’s name; Benson J. Lossing; Charles A. Raymond; John H. Raymond (President of Vassar College, 1864-1878) and Sarah L. Stilson, one of Vassar College’s first students (graduated 1869).
The portion of the collection which deals with Matthew Vassar’s estate “Springside” contains the architect’s drawings. These are housed separately, and can be accessed through the index which is in folder 312, and following page 37 of the register. There is some secondary material on “Springside” in the collection, including some on its recent history, and also some material on Andrew Jackson Downing, the architect and landscape artist.
The exact provenance of much of the memorabilia collection is unknown; those items marked * in the register were transferred to Special Collections from Main Building in 1971.
Items marked with a triple asterisk (***) are a late accession, but whether from the Booth Collection or the 1971 transfer from Main Building is unknown.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Related Materials
Vassar Family Papers
Local History Collection at the Adriance Memorial Library, Poughkeepsie
Separated Materials
Matthew Vassar's canes, spectacles, watch fobs, and other miscellaneous items can be found in the Realia Collection.
Subject Headings
Names:
Anderson, Martin Brewer, 1815-1890; Downing, A.J.(Andrew Jackson), 1815-1852; Hale, Sarah Josepha Buell, 1788-1879; Lossing, Benson J.(Benson John), 1813-1891; Raymond, Charles A.; Raymond, John H.(John Howard), 1814-1878; Stilson, Sarah L.; Vassar, Catherine Valentine
Organizations:
Vassar Brewery (Poughkeepsie, N.Y.); Vassar College--Buildings
Subjects:
Businessmen; Decedents' estates-- New York (State)--Poughkeepsie; Dwellings--New York (State)--Poughkeepsie; Philanthropists; Real property--Michigan; Real property--New York (State)--Poughkeepsie; Women's colleges--New York (State)--Poughkeepsie; Women--Education
Places:
Poughkeepsie (N.Y.)--Commerce; Springside (Poughkeepsie, N.Y.: Estate)
Document Types:
Autobiographies; Autographs; Correspondence; Diaries; Financial records; Maps; Photographs
VCL Categories:
Vassar College Founder
Encoding Information
Encoded by Jennifer Palmentiero, July 2006. Updated by Emma Gronbeck, March 2023.
Acquisition Information
Memorabilia was transferred to Special Collections from Main Building in 1971.
Letters concerning Matthew Vassar's business were the gift of Deling Booth, 1964.
The John Clay note in 23.712 was donated in 2001. (M2014-014)
The framed print of M. Vassar and Co. Brewery by Henry Whinfield was the gift of by Peter Van Kleeck, 2022. (A2022-012)
A Matthew Vassar autograph from 1868 and a tuition receipt from 1867 were the gift of Nathan G. Bein, June 2023. (A2023-038)
Other Formats
1) The Matthew Vassar Papers are also available in microfilm. See also the
Guide to the Matthew Vassar Papers, Microfilm
.
2) A four-volume set of typed transcripts of Matthew Vassar's correspondence was created in 1965 by the Vassar College Library. These volumes are located in the Department of Archives and Special Collections in the Vassariana Collection under the call number, 378.7v FV45A2.
Series List
- Series I. Materials Concerning Vassar College, 1855-1886
  Act to Incorporate
  Notes, Memos, etc. concerning Vassar College
  Correspondence
  Letters of application and draft replies
  Letter book
  College grounds admissions
  Addresses to the Trustees and the college
  Deeds, Mortgages, inventories, etc.
- Series II. Personal and Civic Life, 1815-1975
  Autobiographical writings and diaries
  Baptist Church connections, controversy
  Other civic papers
  Springside
  Miscellaneous personal papers, etc.
  Grave site
  Canes and umbrellas
- Series III. Matthew Vassar and Company, Brewers, 1815-1879
  Memoranda and remarks
  Partnerships
  Financial papers
  The Vassar Brewery (microfilm)
  Lansingburgh Brewery (microfilm)
  Patents
- Series IV. Property and Financial Papers - Personal and Business, 1730-1875
  Deeds in chest
  Deeds
  Deeds pertaining to properties owned by M. Vassar
  Real estate
- Series V. Images, undated
  Silhouettes
  Ambrotype
  Daguerreotypes
- Series VI. Typescripts and Photostats, undated
  This series is largely unprocessed and currently has only minimal description.
Container List
- Series I. Materials Concerning Vassar College
  - Act to incorporate, 18 Jan 1861 (Folder 1.1)
  - "Suggestions in the matters of proceeding with the work of Vassar College" and "Matters for consideration in locating grounds for Vassar Female College,", undated (Folder 1.2)
  - "Mem. remarks made to M. Jewett in my office, 17 Mar 1864 (Folder 1.3)
  - To Hon. Ira Harris, 1 Sep 1860 (Folder 2.4)
  - From Anna Cleveland, 14 Sep 1860 (Folder 2.5)
  - To Miss Anna Clevland, 15 Sep 1860 (Folder 2.6)
  - From Thomas Devan, 25 Sep 1860 (Folder 2.7)
  - To Rev. Thomas Devan, 26 Sep 1860 (Folder 2.8)
  - To Susan B. Anthony, 13 Nov 1860 (Folder 2.9)
  - To Hon. William Kelly, 23 Jan 1861 (Folder 2.10)
  - To Hon. Ira Harris, 24 Jan 1861 (Folder 2.11)
  - From Edwin Morton, Jr., 31 Jan 1861 (Folder 2.12)
  - From W.R. Bartlett, 4 Feb 1861 (Folder 2.13)
  - From William H. DeWitt, 27 Feb 1861 (Folder 2.14)
  - From W.F. Hansell, 1 Mar 1861 (Folder 2.15)
  - To James Grant Wilson, 27 Jun 1861 (Folder 2.16)
  - From Matthew Farrand, 30 Jul 1861 (Folder 2.17)
  - To Matthew Farrand, 30 Jul 1861 (Folder 2.18)
  - To Henry A. Ward, 31 Jul 1861 (Folder 2.19)
  - To Rev. William Hague, 23 Oct 1861 (Folder 2.20)
  - To Mrs. Angela G. Weld, 18 Jul 1862 (Folder 2.21)
  - To Maria Mitchell, 25 Nov 1862 (Folder 2.22)
  - To S.S. Cutting, 6 Jul 1863 (Folder 2.23)
  - To V.C. Board of Trustees, letter from O. Murphy to Trustees, 16 Sep 1863 (Folder 2.24)
  - To Rev. Dr. William Hague, 1 Mar 1864 (Folder 2.25)
  - From William Hague, 2 Mar 1864 (Folder 2.26)
  - From William Kelly, 21 Mar 1864 (Folder 2.27)
  - To William Kelly (draft), [24] Mar 1864 (Folder 2.28)
  - To William Kelly, 24 Mar 1864 (Folder 2.29)
  - To Mrs. M.E.J. Gage, 13 May 1864 (Folder 2.30)
  - To Dear Sir, 11 Jul 1864 (Folder 2.31)
  - To John S. Mann, Esq., 12 Jul 1864 (Folder 2.32)
  - To William Warner, Esq., 20 Jul 1864 (Folder 2.33)
  - To E.L. Magoon, 19 Aug 1864 (Folder 2.34)
  - To Mrs. Sarah Oliphant, 6 Sep 1864 (Folder 2.35)
  - To Eastman, 29 Sep 1865 (Folder 2.36)
  - To Nathan Bishop, 3 Nov 1865 (Folder 2.37)
  - To Miss [M.L.] Dickinson, 10 Mar 1866 (Folder 2.38)
  - To Rev. E.J. Goodspeed, 26 Apr 1866 (Folder 2.39)
  - To Mary L. Gilbert, [1 May] 1866 (Folder 2.40)
  - To M.L. Dickinson, E.L. Talbot, 2 Oct 1866 (Folder 2.41)
  - To Miss [M.H. Whitney], 6 Dec 1866 (Folder 2.42)
  - To Eva Goodrich, 19 Apr 1867 (Folder 2.43)
  - To Jacob P. Giraud, Esq., 20 Apr 1867 (Folder 3.44)
  - To Maria Mitchell, 9 Jul 1867 (Folder 3.45)
  - To Nathan Bishop, 2 Aug 1867 (Folder 3.46)
  - To Miss Powell, 21 Nov 1867 (Folder 3.47)
  - To Dr. [Elias L. Magoon], to honorary committee appointed to inspect the miniature statue..., 12 Dec 1867 (Folder 3.48)
  - To Samuel B. Buckingham, 19 Dec 1867 (Folder 3.49)
  - To Nathan Bishop L.L.D., 10 Jan 1868 (Folder 3.50)
  - To Charles S. Farrar, 10 Mar 1869 (Folder 3.51)
  - To Miss Powell, 28 Apr 1868 (Folder 3.52)
  - To Miss Gilbert, 1 Mar 1868 (Folder 3.53)
  - To Jacob P. Giraud, Esq., 8 Jun 1868 (Folder 3.54)
  - To Prof. Charles S. Farrar, 11 Jun 1868 (Folder 3.55)
  - To Miss Gilbert, undated (Folder 3.56)
  - To Rev. Downing, undated (Folder 3.57)
  - To A.S. Pease, 7 Dec 1862 (Folder 7.194_003)
  - To nephews Matthew, John Guy Vassar, undated (Folder 3.58)
  - To Martin Brewer Anderson, 4 Jul 1855 (Folder 3.59)
  - To Martin Brewer Anderson, 5 Jul 1855 (Folder 3.60)
  - To Martin Brewer Anderson, 3 Mar 1856 (Folder 3.61)
  - To Martin Brewer Anderson, 2 Jul 1856 (Folder 3.62)
  - To Martin Brewer Anderson, 10 Jul 1856 (Folder 3.63)
  - To Martin Brewer Anderson, 19 Jul 1856 (Folder 3.64)
  - To Martin Brewer Anderson, 26 Jan 1859 (Folder 1.65)
  - To Martin Brewer Anderson, 9 Jul 1859 (Folder 3.66)
  - To Martin Brewer Anderson, 24 Mar 1860 (Folder 3.67)
  - To Jacob P. Giraud, 5 Apr 1860 (Folder 3.68)
  - To Martin Brewer Anderson, 8 May 1860 (Folder 3.69)
  - To Martin Brewer Anderson, 19 Jun 1864 (Folder 3.70)
  - To Martin Brewer Anderson, 28 Jan 1864 (Folder 3.71)
  - To Martin Brewer Anderson, 7 May 1865 (Folder 3.72)
  - To Martin Brewer Anderson, 28 Jun 1865 (Folder 3.73)
  - To Martin Brewer Anderson, 5 Jul 1865 (Folder 3.74)
  - To Martin Brewer Anderson, 18 Jun 1866 (Folder 3.75)
  - To Martin Brewer Anderson, 29 Jun 1866 (Folder 3.76)
  - To Sarah J. Hale, 8 May 1860 (Folder 4.77)
  - From Sarah J. Hale, 30 Sep 1860 (Folder 4.78)
  - To Sarah J. Hale, 13 Nov 1861 (Folder 4.79)
  - To Sarah J. Hale, 11 Dec 1862 (Folder 4.80)
  - To Sarah J. Hale, 25 Jan 1864 (Folder 4.81)
  - To Sarah J. Hale, 26 Feb 1864 (Folder 4.82)
  - To Sarah J. Hale, 23 Mar 1864 (Folder 4.83)
  - To Sarah J. Hale, 31 Mar 1864 (Folder 4.84)
  - To Sarah J. Hale, 20 Apr 1864 (Folder 4.85)
  - To Sarah J. Hale, 28 Apr 1864 (Folder 4.86)
  - To Sarah J. Hale, 8 Jun 1864 (Folder 4.87)
  - To Sarah J. Hale, 21 Jun 1864 (Folder 4.88)
  - To Sarah J. Hale, 26 Sep 1864 (Folder 4.89)
  - To Sarah J. Hale, 27 Dec 1864 (Folder 4.90)
  - To Sarah J. Hale, 7 Jan 1865 (Folder 4.91)
  - To Sarah J. Hale, 7 Jan 1865 (Folder 4.92)
  - To Sarah J. Hale, 6 Mar 1865 (Folder 4.93)
  - From Sarah J. Hale, 30 Mar 1865 (Folder 4.94)
  - To Sarah J. Hale, 7 Jun 1865 (Folder 4.95)
  - To Sarah J. Hale, 6 Jul 1865 (Folder 4.96)
  - To Sarah J. Hale, 28 Aug 1865 (Folder 4.97)
  - To Sarah J. Hale, 28 Oct 1865 (Folder 4.98)
  - To Sarah J. Hale, 4 Dec 1865 (Folder 4.99)
  - To Sarah J. Hale, 29 Jan 1866 (Folder 4.100)
  - To Sarah J. Hale, 27 Jun 1866 (Folder 4.101)
  - To Sarah J. Hale, 25 Aug 1866 (Folder 4.102)
  - To Sarah J. Hale, 5 Dec 1866 (Folder 4.103)
  - To Sarah J. Hale, 22 Feb 1867 (Folder 4.104)
  - To Sarah J. Hale, 7 Mar 1867 (Folder 4.105)
  - To Sarah J. Hale, 22 Mar 1867 (Folder 4.106)
  - To Sarah J. Hale, 20 Jun 1867 (Folder 4.107)
  - To Sarah J. Hale, 11 Jul 1867 (Folder 4.108)
  - To Sarah J. Hale, 9 Sep 1867 (Folder 4.109)
  - To Sarah J. Hale, 3 Oct 1867 (Folder 4.110)
  - To Sarah J. Hale, 14 Oct 1867 (Folder 4.111)
  - To Sarah J. Hale, 27 Mar 1868 (Folder 4.112)
  - To Sarah J. Hale, undated (Folder 4.113)
  - From Milo P. Jewett, [Summer?] 1863 (Folder 5.114)
  - To Milo P. Jewett, 24 Oct 1863 (Folder 1.115)
  - To Milo P. Jewett, 2 Mar 1864 (Folder 5.116)
  - To Milo P. Jewett, 17 Mar 1864 (Folder 5.117)
  - To Milo P. Jewett, 19 Mar 1864 (Folder 5.118)
  - To Milo P. Jewett, 22 Mar 1864 (Folder 5.119)
  - To Benson J. Lossing, 14 Feb 1861 (Folder 5.120)
  - To Benson J. Lossing, 29 Sep 1862 (Folder 5.121)
  - To Benson J. Lossing, 24 May 1864 (Folder 5.122)
  - To Benson J. Lossing, 27 Jun 1866 (Folder 5.123)
  - To Benson J. Lossing, 4 Feb 1867 (Folder 5.124)
  - To Benson J. Lossing, 15 Feb 1867 (Folder 5.125)
  - To Benson J. Lossing, 22 Feb 1867 (Folder 5.126)
  - "Bill chargeable to M. Vassar for work done on..."Vassar College and the Founder" by Benson J. Lossing, [Jun?] 1867 (Folder 5.902)
  - To Benson J. Lossing, 15 Jun 1867 (Folder 5.127)
  - To Benson J. Lossing, 1 Jul 1867 (Folder 5.128)
  - To Benson J. Lossing, 2 Jul 1867 (Box 41)
  - To Rev. Charles A. Raymond, 30 Jul 1862 (Folder 5.129)
  - To Rev. Charles A. Raymond, 6 Aug 1862 (Folder 5.130)
  - To Rev. Charles A. Raymond, 9 Aug 1862 (Folder 5.131)
  - To Rev. Charles A. Raymond, 25 Aug 1862 (Folder 5.132)
  - To Rev. Charles A. Raymond, 28 Aug 1862 (Folder 5.133)
  - To Rev. Charles A. Raymond, 12 Sep 1862 (Folder 5.134)
  - To Rev. Charles A. Raymond, 16 Sep 1862 (Folder 5.135)
  - To Rev. Charles A. Raymond, 22 Sep 1862 (Folder 5.136)
  - To Rev. Charles A. Raymond, 25 Nov 1862 (Folder 5.137)
  - To Rev. Charles A. Raymond, 12 Dec 1862 (Folder 5.138)
  - To Rev. Charles A. Raymond, 29 Dec 1862 (Folder 5.139)
  - To Rev. Charles A. Raymond, 1 Jan 1863 (Folder 5.140)
  - To Rev. Charles A. Raymond, 6 Feb 1863 (Folder 5.141)
  - To Rev. Charles A. Raymond, 24 Feb 1863 (Folder 5.142)
  - To Rev. Charles A. Raymond, 13 Mar 1863 (Folder 5.143)
  - To Rev. Charles A. Raymond, 20 Mar 1863 (Folder 5.144)
  - To Rev. Charles A. Raymond, 24 May 1863 (Folder 5.145)
  - To Rev. Charles A. Raymond, 13 Aug 1863 (Folder 5.146)
  - To Rev. Charles A. Raymond, 3 Apr 1864 (Folder 5.147)
  - To Rev. Charles A. Raymond, typescripts of letters in folders 129-147, 30 Jul 1862 - 3 Apr 1864 (Folder 5.148)
  - To John H. Raymond, 24 Jan 1861 (Folder 5.149)
  - To John H. Raymond, 2 Jun 1864 (Folder 5.150)
  - To John H. Raymond, 17 Jun 1864 (Folder 5.151)
  - To John H. Raymond, 12 Aug 1864 (Folder 5.152)
  - To John H. Raymond, 22 Dec 1864 (Folder 5.153)
  - To John H. Raymond, 14 Jan 1865 (Folder 5.154)
  - To John H. Raymond, 7 Nov 1865 (Folder 6.155)
  - To John H. Raymond, 29 Nov 1866 (Folder 6.156)
  - To John H. Raymond, 5 Feb 1867 (Folder 6.157)
  - To John H. Raymond, 14 Feb 1868 (Folder 6.158)
  - To John H. Raymond, 10 Jun 1868 (Folder 6.159)
  - To Mrs. John H. Raymond, undated (Folder 6.160)
  - To Cyrus Swan, Jun 1861 (Folder 6.161)
  - To Cyrus Swan, 10 Jan 1862 (Folder 6.162)
  - To Cyrus Swan, [1865?] (Folder 6.163)
  - To Cyrus Swan, 2 Nov 1865 (Folder 6.164)
  - To Cyrus Swan, 22 Feb 1866 (Folder 6.165)
  - From Cyrus Swan, 30 Mar 1868 (Folder 6.166)
  - From Cyrus Swan, 4 Apr 1868 (Folder 6.167)
  - To Cyrus Swan, 10 Apr 1868 (Folder 6.168)
  - To Cyrus Swan, 10 Apr 1868 (Folder 6.169)
  - From Cyrus Swan, 2 May 1868 (Folder 6.170)
  - From Cyrus Swan, 6 May 1868 (Folder 6.171)
  - To Sarah L. Stilson, 8 May 1866 (Folder 6.172)
  - To Sarah L. Stilson, 18 Jun 1866 (Folder 6.173)
  - To Sarah L. Stilson, 4 May 1867 (Folder 6.174)
  - To Sarah L. Stilson, [13 Jun] 1867 (Folder 6.175)
  - From Sarah L. Stilson, 21 Aug 1867 (Folder 6.176)
  - Care of Sarah L. Stilson, 5 Sep 1867 (Folder 6.177)
  - From Sarah L. Stilson, 21 Sep 1867 (Folder 6.178)
  - Care of Sarah L. Stilson, 26 Sep 1867 (Folder 6.179)
  - From Sarah L. Stilson, 12 Oct 1867 (Folder 6.180)
  - To Sarah L. Stilson, 18 Oct 1867 (Folder 6.181)
  - From Sarah L. Stilson, 6 Dec 1867 (Folder 6.182)
  - To Sarah L. Stilson, 10 Dec 1867 (Folder 6.183)
  - From Carrie F. Stowe, 7 Nov 1861 (Folder 6.184)
  - To Carrie F. Stowe, 29 Nov 1861 (Folder 6.185)
  - From Carrie F. Stowe, 3 Jun 1862 (Folder 6.186)
  - To Carrie F. Stowe, 10 Jun 1862 (Folder 6.187)
  - To Carrie F. Stowe, 25 Jun 1862 (Folder 6.188)
  - From Carrie F. Stowe, 12 Feb 1862 (Folder 6.189)
  - From Carrie F. Stowe, 22 Feb 1862 (Folder 6.190)
  - Letters of application and draft replies
    - From J. Donnolly, Jr., 24 Oct 1860 (Folder 7.191_001)
    - From Maggie [House] Strong, 26 Mar 1861 (Folder 7.191_002)
    - From Clara B. Dourey, 27 Mar 1861 (Folder 7.191_003)
    - To Kate Dinehart, 25 Mar 1861 (Folder 7.191_004)
    - From Kate Dinehart, 23 Mar 1861 (Folder 7.191_005)
    - From Mary Tourne, 1 Jun 1861 (Folder 7.191_006)
    - To Ida P. Whitman, 3 Apr 1861 (Folder 7.191_007)
    - From Grace Hoyle, 12 Jun 1861 (Folder 7.191_008)
    - To Grace Hoyle, 20 Jun 1861 (Folder 7.191_009)
    - From Daniel H. Herr, 30 Jul 1861 (Folder 7.191_010)
    - To Daniel H. Herr, 1 Aug 1861 (Folder 7.191_011)
    - From Emily Williams, 16 Mar 1862 (Folder 7.192_001)
    - To Emily Williams, 18 Mar 1862 (Folder 7.192_002)
    - From Eliza L. May, 24 Mar 1862 (Folder 7.192_003)
    - To Eliza L. May, 28 Mar 1862 (Folder 7.192_004)
    - From Albert N. Goble, 14 May 1862 (Folder 7.192_005)
    - From Mrs. M.E.J. Gage, 20 Jun 1862 (Folder 7.192_006)
    - To Mrs. M.E. Gage, 25 Jun 1862 (Folder 7.192_007)
    - From Angeline G. Weld, 21 Jun 1862 (Folder 7.192_008)
    - To Mrs. Angeline G. Weld, 30 Jun 1862 (Folder 7.192_009)
    - From Laura E. Harris, 28 Jun 1862 (Folder 7.193_001)
    - To Laura E. Harris, 28 Jun 1862 (Folder 7.193_002)
    - From Mr. C.H. Smith, 15 Jul 1862 (Folder 7.193_003)
    - To Mr. C.H. Smith, 17 Jul 1862 (Folder 7.193_004)
    - From Reverend E.G. Goodspeed, Jul 1862 (Folder 7.193_005)
    - To Reverend E.G. Goodspeed, 23 Jul 1862 (Folder 7.193_006)
    - From Carrie E. Atwood, 10 Sep 1862 (Folder 7.193_007)
    - To Carrie E. Atwood, 23 Oct 1862 (Folder 7.193_008)
    - From E.H. Hubbard, 11 Oct 1862 (Folder 7.193_009)
    - To E.H. Hubbard, 14 Oct 1862 (Folder 7.193_010)
    - From Gertrude .E. Smith, 1 Dec 1862 (Folder 7.194_001)
    - To G.E. Smith, 6 Dec 1862 (Folder 7.194_002)
    - From Olive L. Huntley, 5 Dec 1862 (Folder 7.194_004)
    - From Mary A. Hubbell, 11 Dec 1862 (Folder 7.194_005)
    - To Mary A. Hubbell, 20 Dec 1862 (Folder 7.194_006)
    - From Mrs. Sarah M. Perkins, 11 Dec 1862 (Folder 7.194_007)
    - To Mrs. Sarah M. Perkins, 16 Dec 1862 (Folder 7.194_008)
    - From Emilie S. Lawton, 12 Dec 1862 (Folder 7.194_009)
    - To Emilie S. Lawton, 19 Dec 1862 (Folder 7.194_010)
    - From Miss G. Anderson, 15 Dec 1862 (Folder 7.194_011)
    - To Miss Anderson, 18 Dec 1862 (Folder 7.194_012)
    - From F. A. Gray, 23 Dec 1862 (Folder 7.194_013)
    - To F.A. Gray, 27 Dec 1862 (Folder 7.194_014)
    - From Hellen M. Tidd, 26 Dec 1862 (Folder 7.194_015)
    - To Helen M. Tidd, 26 Dec 1862 (Folder 7.194_016)
    - From Lizzie Thomas, 1 Jan 1863 (Folder 7.195_001)
    - To Lizzie Thomas, 7 Jan 1863 (Folder 7.195_002)
    - From Mrs. Fairchild Judd, 8 Jan 1863 (Folder 7.195_003)
    - To Mrs. Fairchild Judd, 9 Jan 1863 (Folder 7.195_004)
    - From George D. Goodrich, 14 Jan 1863 (Folder 7.195_005)
    - To George D. Goodrich, 16 Jan 1863 (Folder 7.195_006)
    - From Anna E. Murphy, 29 Jan 1863 (Folder 7.195_007)
    - To Anna E. Murphy, 4 Feb 1863 (Folder 7.195_008)
    - [C.Van Keuren?] letter of application on behalf of daughter Annette, 4 Feb 1863 (Folder 7.196_001)
    - From Grace D. Dickerson, 9 Feb 1863 (Folder 7.196_002)
    - To Grace D. Dickerson, 13 Feb 1863 (Folder 7.196_003)
    - To Braidward, 26 Jan 1863 (Folder 7.196_004)
    - From Mrs. R.E. Knight, 13 Feb 1863 (Folder 7.196_005)